<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meta | Yet another programming blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://xaerxess.github.io/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://xaerxess.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-23T21:46:14+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://xaerxess.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Grzegorz Rożniecki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MANIFEST - or (future) content of this blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://xaerxess.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/manifest-or-future-content-of-this-blog.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T00:04:43+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://xaerxess.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/manifest-or-future-content-of-this-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m starting a programming blog (again). I don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;ll be successful (where successful = updated regularly), but I&rsquo;d like to start with meta-post about what I <em>want</em> to have here. Since I&rsquo;ve been (proffesionally) working as a <a href="http://www.perl.org/">Perl</a>, Java and JavaScript developer for few years, vast amount of topics will be about these programming languages, with Perl being main one.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Short clarification here: Perl has a facinating community with really, really great developers, and if you look back to previous sentence you&rsquo;ll see that I only linked to Perl webpage, contrary to Java and JavaScript. The reason is simple &ndash; these two J* languages have no proper webpages and no <em>(open-source)</em> community. You can go to java.<strong>com</strong> and click big red download button, but that&rsquo;s all. Google &ldquo;java&rdquo; and you&rsquo;ll see &ldquo;Oracle&rdquo; and &ldquo;™&rdquo; higher than &ldquo;OpenJDK&rdquo;. Typing JavaScript in Google gives you <strong>zero</strong> language/community hits (let me just say that w3schools is first one); <a href="http://www.ecmascript.org/">ECMAScript</a> is all about standards and many JS devs aren&rsquo;t be able to tell what ECMAScript is.</p>

<p>On the other hand, googling &ldquo;perl&rdquo; gives you hits like:</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;The Perl Programming Language &ndash; www.perl.org&rdquo;,</li>
<li>&ldquo;Perl programming documentation &ndash; perldoc.perl.org&rdquo;,</li>
<li>&ldquo;The Comprehensive Perl Archive Network &ndash; www.cpan.org&rdquo;,</li>
<li>&ldquo;Strawberry Perl for Windows&rdquo;,</li>
<li>&ldquo;Perl Monks&rdquo;,</li>
<li>&ldquo;The Perl Foundation&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>from which <strong>every single resource is awesome</strong> &ndash; if you&rsquo;ve been using Perl for a while, you just can&rsquo;t <em>not</em> appreciate whole ecosystem and say <em>Perl is dead</em> because it&rsquo;s simply not true at all.</p>

<p>Besides writing about software engineering and programming languages, because I believe in free and open-source software and culture, I&rsquo;ll probably cover these topics, too. (Lately <a href="https://github.com/Xaerxess">I started contributing</a> to various open-source projects, I&rsquo;ve been using GNU/Linux <a href="http://linuxcounter.net/user/407987.html">for almost nine years</a>, I really enjoy both). For now, I&rsquo;d like to point you to <a href="http://pjf.id.au/ethics/2013/12/28/do-not-stifle-innovation.html">this blog post</a> (by <a href="https://twitter.com/pjf">@pjf</a>) which I fully agree with:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;While I’ve always known open source software is great, I’m increasingly starting to appreciate that open source developers are also great.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>What&rsquo;s more, I&rsquo;d like to share everything on this site for free, so I&rsquo;m making all my code available under <a href="http://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT license</a> (unless marked otherwise) and all my writing available under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution license</a>. You can grab the code of this blog is on <a href="https://github.com/Xaerxess/xaerxess.github.io">GitHub</a>, use it, fork it, modify it, etc. I&rsquo;ll also be grateful for all suggestions and for spelling or grammar fixes because blogging in English and not being native English speaker is a challenge.</p>

<p>Anyway, enjoy reading, consider leaving a comment or following me on some social media, and have a nice day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
